<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Yorke before the right Honorable, Henrie Earle of Huntington, Lorde President of her Maiesties councell established in the north, and other noble men, and gentle men, at a general communion there, the 23. of September in the eightienth yeare of her Maiesties raigne: by Mathewe Hutton Deane of Yorke.</title>
            <author>Hutton, Matthew, 1529-1606.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 83 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104336</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840074</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4545</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03926)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4545)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 250:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Yorke before the right Honorable, Henrie Earle of Huntington, Lorde President of her Maiesties councell established in the north, and other noble men, and gentle men, at a general communion there, the 23. of September in the eightienth yeare of her Maiesties raigne: by Mathewe Hutton Deane of Yorke.</title>
                  <author>Hutton, Matthew, 1529-1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 29, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By Thomas Dawson] for Richard Sergier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Jeremiah VI, 16.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4545:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4545:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at Yorke, before the right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Henrie Earle of Huntington, Lorde Preſident of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Councell eſtabliſhed in the North, and other noble men, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, at a general Communion there, the 23. of September in the eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienth yeare of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties raigne:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Mathewe Hutton Deane of Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, for Richard Sergier. Anno. 1579.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4545:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4545:2"/>
            <head>W. C. ¶ To the Reader, the <hi>knowledge &amp; bleſſinges</hi> of the trueth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the zeale &amp; ſtrength of our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, the Queene, was verie great to the prayſe of God, and the bleſſednes of hir king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in bringing the Goſpell by a reentrie into this lande, when the Lorde brought her, in his rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto the kingdome: So her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties care hath beene from time to time great alſo, by the preaching of the worde, by many good Lawes, by the authoritie and countenance
<pb facs="tcp:4545:3"/>
of her Magiſtrates, to further the courſe and aduaunce the eſtimation thereof, to the releeuing of the people from that darkeneſſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they walked: that comming to the light of the trueth, they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come children of the light, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritoures of the life, which is in Chriſte Ieſus. This hath appeared manie wayes in manie places, and namely in her Prouince of York, at a ſolemne aſſemblie of the honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and woorſhipful of thoſe partes: where after a verie learned and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sermon, fitte for that aſſemblie and action, they were together par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Lordes table, to teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie to God their religion, to ſhewe their obedience to her Maieſties proceedings, and to leaue it witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the whole worlde, that they embrace the Goſpell, and labour, by their example, to drawe others alſo
<pb facs="tcp:4545:3"/>
to the loue of the ſame trueth.</p>
            <p>Touching the Sermon, For the Authors greate learning and good Spirite, it muſt carrie great prayſe with as many as knowe him, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially with them, that knowe him beſt. As manie as knowe him not, may in reading it, beholde the good graces of God in him, for the worke of the Goſpell, and a notable ſpirite plainelie and ſoundly confuting the chiefeſt groundes of the Popiſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: vpon which ſandie groundes notwithſtanding (though they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Peter to be the rocke) manie builde, not foreſeeing the ruire and great fall of the houſe.</p>
            <p>For, Antiquitie and Generalitie are good markes of the church, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with better: alone, they may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well iuſtifie ſinne and errour, as the Romiſhe Churche. Thoſe other chiefe markes it hath not, the true
<pb facs="tcp:4545:4"/>
and pure vſe of the woorde and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, But as it wanteth the chiefeſt markes of the Churche of Chriſte, whiche deceiue not: So it hath vndoubted ſignes of the church of Antichriſt, a doctrine preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the offices and merites of Chriſte, a foundation that GOD hath not layed, the perſecutions of Antichriſt, the blaſphemies of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, the marchandiſes of the greate whore of Babylon, and the marke of the beaſte. O that they, which haue trafique with her, would come out of the Merchauntes falſe lighte, and might haue their eyes open, and their heartes alſo, to conſider what ſtuffe they haue for their ſoules laid in pawne to her, for payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of their obedience and tribute.</p>
            <p>As for their iuſtification by workes and not by faith onely, it doeth plainely ſhewe, they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande
<pb facs="tcp:4545:4"/>
neither the imperfection of their perfecteſt woorkes, nor the grace of GOD, which ſaueth them, that beleeue thorow faith in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of Chriſte alone. Whiche faith notwithſtanding neceſſarily bringeth foorth good woorkes, not meritorious cauſes, but manifeſt notes to vs of our ſaluation in the merites of Chriſte Ieſus the Lorde and Sauiour.</p>
            <p>In that they forbid the people to read the ſcriptures: they commit too too manifeſt violence, in withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, in diſpoſſeſſing vs of our fathers laſt will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. How ſhall they demaund the legacie, that know not the gift? How ſhall they keepe the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that know not the couenaunt? If they ſay the ſcriptures are hard, they ſpeake (to ſay no woorſe) igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, of the will or power of God
<pb facs="tcp:4545:5"/>
that either would not, or could not ſpeake plainely, and to the hart of his people, to the vnderſtanding of his children. But as the children of this worlde, they were wiſe in their generation: they kept that backe, which might bring the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God forward: they put the light vnder a busſhell, that it might not ſhine to thoſe that came into the houſe. Darkenes did beſt ſet out and moſt mainteine the workes of darkenes. Neuertheleſſe, ſure it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God for his glory, to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vnto manie, cauſing the light to ſhine out of darkenes, and bringing this euidence into light, and the light therof into the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſonnes of men. They (as many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as appertaine to the holy electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God) haue had eyes to ſee, and hartes to conſider, what it is to walk in darkeneſſe, and in the ſhadowe of
<pb facs="tcp:4545:5"/>
death, what it is to lye faſt bound in Babylon in miſerie and yron, and what it is to dwell in the houſe of God, to beholde his beautie, and to viſite his holy temple, to ſerue the Lord, and to wayte for the fulneſſe of his rich mercies in Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde. As for the ſufficiencie of the Scriptures, if no man maye adde any thing, there wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: If no man may take any thing away, there is nothing too much. Wherevppon they that haue eyes to ſee and will ſee, may beholde that the ſcriptures are all ſufficient and perfect: dangerous therefore is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie doctrine of Hoſius, one of the Maiſter Maſons at the greate building of Trent: But his doctrine is lately and ſufficiently confuted.</p>
            <p>Whereas they denye ſome, the lawful remedie againſt fornication, theire deeds bewray their doctrine:
<pb facs="tcp:4545:6"/>
for they not regarding it, died in the diſeaſe, whereof they condemned the remedie.</p>
            <p>For the Inuocation of Saintes, and the doctrine of the newe media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourſhip to the Mediatour, which is but one, it ſheweth a greate faith and truſt in thoſe Saintes, as being more readie and willing to helpe, where they promiſe no helpe, then God, that dooth both promiſe, and keepe the couenaunt of mercie made to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham and his ſeede, euen as many of them, as ſeeke the face of God, and walke in newenes of life, which is the true ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the <hi>Iſraell</hi> of God. But if Saintes can be neither ſo able, (if they be able at al) nor ſo willing to heare &amp; helpe vs, as is the mightie &amp; moſt louing God of our ſaluation, why doo any in a blinde niceneſſe ſtraine curteſie, to pray vnto God, which is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:6"/>
and make no conſcience to giue his honour to others, which is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
            <p>Concerning the maſſe, it hath been long agoe publikelie indited, and truely condemned of groſſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie and forgerie. Saint Paule in that greate myſterie, teſtifieth for himſelf to the Corinthians, That he added nothing to the ſimple inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lordes ſupper: but what he receiued, that he redeliuered, and what he receiued not, that he deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not at all. But they of the Maſſe haue deliuered in charge to be bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and receiued, a bodie without quantitie or qualitie, a ſacrifice for the quicke and deade, a woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, a reſeruation, and ſuch like ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions and abhominations, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique (I graunt) and olde borne in reſpect of theſe times: but neither they nor their mother conceiued in
<pb facs="tcp:4545:7"/>
reſpect of the Apoſtles time.</p>
            <p>Theſe pointes, that I haue but in a woorde or two noted, are plainely and learnedly handled in this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: I truſt in the mercie of God, to the redeeming of manie from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour that heard it, or, without a ſet iudgement againſt the truth ſhall diligently reade it. Others, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie embrace the truth, and yet in opinion rather then in reaſon and iudgement, (of which ſort I would there were not many) may heere receiue reaſons out of the woorde of god, to confirme their good zeale and iudgment, to anſweare for them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues and their religion, when they ſhal either be aſked a reaſon of their hope and faith of the brethren, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſhall be aſſayled of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie. For, good Reader, labour and prouoke others to labour, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe vnder thy charge, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie
<pb facs="tcp:4545:7"/>
to anſweare for theire religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and to ſhew better euidence for their inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in heauen, then any man can ſhew vppon record for his inheritance on the earth.</p>
            <p>Therfore I deſire thee, not ſo much in theſe wordes, which I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in loue to the matter, &amp; the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, as I craue it in my heart at thy hand, to make thy fruite of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt preached, to kindle flames of zeale in the hearers, to their increaſe of knowledg, &amp; a good conſcience: And nowe allowed to the print in the ſame godly purpoſe, to nouriſh &amp; preſerue the ſame zeale with great increaſe in all the readers, eſpecially of thoſe, that haue already heard it, &amp; may now reade the ſame againe: which will be as the former and latter raine, to make the fruite ripe, and full in Chriſt Ieſus. Which fruite that thou maiſt reape, I leaue
<pb facs="tcp:4545:8"/>
thee to the woorke and inſtruction of Gods holy Spirit, praying thee, when in hearing or reading theſe Sermons, thou findeſt the rich trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge and faith, to pray earneſtly to God, that the ſame moſt rich treaſure of his woorde may be plentifully beſtowed vppon all men in all places farre and neare, to the euerlaſting glory of Gods holy name, in gathering thoſe, that are to be gathered and in keeping them, that are alreadie gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4545:8"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ierem.</hi> 6.16.</bibl>
                  <p>State ſuper vias, &amp; videte &amp; interrogate de ſemitis antiquis, quae ſit via bona? &amp; ambulate in ea: &amp; inuenietis refri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerium animabus veſtris. Stand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the wayes, conſider, and inquire of the olde wayes, which is good, and walke therein: and ye ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the</hi> time of the Prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie, there was greate contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the preachers of the woorde, the true teachers of the people of God, and the falſe Prophets. For thone threatened warre, and captiuitie vnto the people, for the great wickedneſſe of the land: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid: <hi>Pax, pax. All ſhould bee well.</hi> Thone ſaid: <hi>Templum Domini, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum
<pb facs="tcp:4545:9"/>
Domini: The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> &amp; that the Lorde would neuer deſtroy that holy place: the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cried, that the houſe of God was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a denne of theues: &amp; the Lord would ſurely viſit that place. The one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the ceremonies, &amp; rites of the law, &amp; exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the people to offer vp their ſacrifices, as moſt ſweete &amp; pleaſant to the Lord the other ſaid, that their incenſe oblations &amp; burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings were to him an abhomination, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were offered without faith, the only ſalt &amp; ſeaſoner of al our works. The one cried the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thelders, the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the fathers, the other anſwered, that they worſhipped God in vaine, teaching for doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceptes of men. In this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there were manie (eſpeciallie of the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eſt ſort, that doubted whom to beleeue, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to miſtruſt, which way to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid, &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h to walke in. And therefore the Prophet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> bringeth in, in this place al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d himſelfe ſpeaking to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what they ſhould doe. <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſuper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s, &amp; videte, &amp;c. Stand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the waies &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſider, &amp;c.</hi> In which wordes, he wille<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to be careleſſe in things touching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ir ſaluation, but ſtudious pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full &amp; la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ous. <hi>Stand vpon the waies &amp;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4545:9"/>
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, inquire, &amp;c.</hi> 2. He ſheweth them, where to ſeeke the beſt <hi>way,</hi> not in <hi>newe wayes</hi> founde out of late, but in the <hi>waies</hi> that haue bene of old time: <hi>Aſke of the old waies, &amp;c.</hi> Thirdly he would not haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinke euerie <hi>old way</hi> to bee walked in, &amp; therfore willeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, among the <hi>old waies, to ſearch the beſt, &amp; walk therin:</hi> laſt of al to incorage the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to folow his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, he tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what they ſhal gaine thereby: <hi>And you ſhall finde reſt vnto your ſoules.</hi> The ſame doctrine is as needefull to vs now, as it was then to them, ſeing the ſame occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is among vs at this time, that was among them. For while there is great diſputation euerie where in matters of religion, while the <hi>Papiſtes</hi> ſhew one <hi>way</hi> to ſaluation, the Proteſtantes an other: the papiſtes ſay, <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Domini, templum Domini: The holy Church of Rome, the holy catholik church of Rome,</hi> the proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts replie, <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cta eſt meretrix vrbs fidelis: &amp; that ſhe is now become the whore of Babilon:</hi> the papiſts ſay, The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions of the church the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our mother the church: the Proteſtantes anſwere, that they worſhip god in vaine, teaching for doctrine, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ther are many that haue waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring minds, &amp; know not what way to take:
<pb facs="tcp:4545:10"/>
To them no doubt, the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet is verie good: <hi>Let them ſtand vpon the waies &amp; conſider, and inquire of the old wayes, which is beſt, &amp; walk therein: &amp; they ſhall finde reſt vnto their ſoules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The text conteineth theſe two pointes, the Counſel, and the Commoditie enſuing: The Counſell is, <hi>To ſtande vppon the wayes, and conſider, to aſke of the olde wayes: which is beſt, &amp; to walke therein.</hi> The fruite that will grow thereof: is, <hi>That wee ſhall finde reſt vnto our ſoules.</hi> But becauſe I can not ſpeake of euery parcell at large, I haue choſen to intreate onelie of theſe two pointes ſhewed vnto me by the text, and by the time required at my hands. Firſt verie briefly, that we muſt ſeeke the <hi>good waie</hi> among the <hi>olde waies,</hi> and yet not euerie <hi>olde way</hi> to be walked in: Secondlie by a briefe diſcourſe, through the chiefeſt pointes of religion, I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that that <hi>olde way</hi> is the beſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Fathers walked by the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of almightie God: and that alſo that is the <hi>Oldeſt way</hi> of all, &amp; that corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Poperie is a way of later time fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out. The which thing that I may do, ſo that the name of God may be glorified, and wee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4545:10"/>
that be here preſent edified, I ſhall deſire you, to aſſiſt me w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your hartie prayer. &amp;c.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Tand vppon the wayes, and conſider, &amp;c.</hi> Hee would not haue vs negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in thinges pertei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to our ſaluation, but vigilant, and painefull to finde out, and to know the truth. He tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs where to ſeke, among the <hi>Olde wayes.</hi> Loe, Antiquitie is one noate, or marke of Veritie. <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> ſaith: there bee three eſpeciall markes or badges, to know which is true Doctrine in the Church, <hi>Antiquitie, Vniuerſalitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antiquitie,</note> and <hi>Conſent.</hi> And ſurely where theſe three co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curre in the church, there is no doubt but there is the truth, there is the <hi>Good way,</hi> wherin we ſhold walke. But becauſe truth dwelleth as a ſtranger heere on earth, and hath more enimies then friendes, ſhee fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not ſo much curteſie amongeſt men, to bee ſuffered to weare all wayes all theſe three badges: Therefore the ſame <hi>Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> aſketh the queſtion, what is to bee doone, if error doe inuade the greater part of the Church, and bee mainteined with
<pb facs="tcp:4545:11"/>
Conſent of the greater part? He anſwereth that in ſuch caſe, we muſt flie to <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> He giueth an example: The wicked doctrine of <hi>Arrius</hi> had once almoſt infected all Chriſtendome: <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was an <hi>Arrian: Liberius</hi> Biſhop of Rome an <hi>Arrian</hi> for a time, and gaue his handwriting againſt the diuinitie of our Sauiour Chriſt: almoſt all the Biſhops in the worlde did yeelde to that blaſphemy: he ſaith, <hi>That in this caſe, the former time muſt be conſidered, what was the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Church, before Arrius began to ſpread his hereſie, &amp; that is the truth.</hi> For it goeth not with religion, as it doeth with the ſtatutes of the Realme, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes at common Law, where the later is thought the better: For in religion, the firſt and <hi>oldeſt</hi> is the <hi>beſt.</hi> The doctrine of the Church is older than anie Idolatrie or ſuperſtition of the Gentiles, the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was preached in Paradiſe by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the Serpentes heade,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> The writing of <hi>Moſes</hi> older than anie writing of the Gentiles, The doctrine of the Apoſtles, older than Poperie, or anie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4545:11"/>
hereſie. <hi>Tertullian</hi> againſt <hi>Praxeas,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quod peraequè aduerſus omnes haereſes preiudicatum ſit, id eſſe verum quodcunque primum id eſſe adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quodcunque poſterius. This muſt bee taken as a rule to preiudice all here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, that that is true whiche is firſte, that counterfeit &amp; falſe, which is brought in afterward.</hi> Truth it is that <hi>Baſilius</hi> ſaith to <hi>Amphilochius <hi>cap. 29.</hi> Perſuaſiua ſunt quodammodo vetera dogmata, velut in antiquitate canicie quadam reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quiddam habentia. Olde religion is apt to perſwade men to imbrace it.</hi> For why? <hi>The antiquitie thereof is as it were gray heares, &amp; hoare head, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth men to reuerence it.</hi> Yet muſt we take heede, that we be not mooued with the onely name of <hi>Antiquitie,</hi> that we be not deceiued with a viſard, or coloured white heade and bearde. For truth manie times is accuſed of Noueltie and errour, &amp; much commended for the Antiquitie. When the Goſpell of Chriſt was firſte preached vnto the Gentills, it ſeemed newe vnto them, and they alleaged Antiquitie, for the defence of their idolatrous religion.
<pb facs="tcp:4545:12"/>
                  <hi>Act. <hi>17. May wee not knowe</hi>
                  </hi> (ſay the Philoſophers) <hi>what newe Doctrine is this, whereof thou ſpeakeſt?</hi> And in the <hi>19. <hi>chap.</hi> Demetrius</hi> the Siluerſmith, and the Towneclarke of <hi>Epheſus</hi> alledge not onely vniuerſalitie, but alſo antiquitie for their goddeſſe <hi>Diana.</hi> And <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his booke <hi>De iuſtitia</hi> ſayth: <hi>Deorum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores libenter errant, &amp; ſtultitiae ſuae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, a quibus ſi rationem requiras per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſionis eius, nullam poſſunt reddere, ſed ad maiorum iudicia confugiunt, quòd illi ſapientes fuerint, &amp;c. The worſhippers of falſe Gods are willinglie deceiued, and flatter themſelues in their owne follie, of whom if you aſke a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their conſcience, they can yeelde none, but flie to their forefathers, and ſay, that they were wiſe men, and not like to bee deceiued.</hi> And <hi>Symmachus</hi> that famous Senator, but ſworne enimie to Chriſtes religion, writeth thus, (as <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius</hi> ſaith <hi>Lib. 2.) <hi>Si longa aetas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem religionibus faciat, ſeruanda eſt tot ſaeculis fides, &amp; ſequendi ſunt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis parentes, qui foeliciter ſecuti ſunt ſuos. If continuance of time giue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to religion, wee muſt ſtill giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4545:12"/>
to ſo manie hundred yeares, ſince the dayes of King Numa, a thouſande yeares at the leaſt: and wee muſt folowe our fathers, who moſt happely followed their forefathers.</hi>
                  </hi> Loe, they did not exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the <hi>waies</hi> of theire fathers, whether they were good or euill, yet would they needes folow them, &amp; thought Antiquitie a ſufficient argument ſo to doe. I reade of one <hi>Radbodus</hi> King of the <hi>Phriſians,</hi> a Panim, that when he was perſuaded to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Chriſtian, and was readie to bee baptized, and had one foote in the fount, he ſtaied, and aſked the Biſhoppe, what was become of all his progenitours, and which <hi>Way</hi> they were gone, that were neuer chriſtened, nor beleued in Chriſt? The Bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop anſwered, that without baptiſme, and the faith of Chriſt, he had no warrant, but to ſay, that they were gone to hell: he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out his legge againe out of the water, <hi>Surely,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>I will goe with them for companie.</hi> So a great ſort had rather erre with their forefathers, thento embrace the truth, if it ſeeme vnto them newe. <hi>Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conius</hi> the heretike could ſay to S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine: Our fathers receiued this of theire fathers: Truth,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine. Sed er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes
<pb facs="tcp:4545:13"/>
ab errantibus: As the Iewes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of their fathers, that the bodie of Chriſt was ſtolne out of the ſepulchre: but being falſe at the beginning, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of time will not make it true.</hi> Therefore if our fathers erre, wee may not folow them, neither is euerie <hi>olde way good,</hi> but that onely, wherein our fathers haue walked by the commaundement of God, as ſhewed vnto them by his holy woorde. Therefore the Prophet willeth vs to aſke of the <hi>old waies, which is good, and walke in it,</hi> And <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith: <hi>Stand vpon the wayes:</hi> that is, <hi>vpon the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets:</hi> they be the <hi>wayes,</hi> that will bring vs to Chriſt, who is the <hi>way, the truth and life,</hi> And <hi>Tertull</hi> againſt <hi>Marcian</hi> ſayth: <hi>Conſtat id verius, quod prius, id prius, quod ab initio, id ab initio, quod ab Apoſtolis traditum. It is plaine, that that is the trueſt, which is firſt, that firſte which was from the beginning, that from the beginning, which was deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Apoſtles.</hi> Againſt which way no Cuſtome though it be neuer ſo old, may preuaile. Chriſt ſaid that he was <hi>Trueth,</hi> &amp; did not ſay that he was Cuſtome. <hi>Cyprian, Epiſt. ad Pompeium. Conſuetudo ſine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4545:13"/>
veritate vetuſtas erroris eſt. Cuſtome without truth, is nothing elſe but an old error.</hi> And <hi>Lib. 2. Epiſt. 3. <hi>Non debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus attendere quid aliquis ante nos fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum putauerit, ſed quid, qui ante omnes eſt, Chriſtus prior fecerit. Wee muſt not regarde what any man, before vs, hath ſuppoſed good to be done, but what Chriſt did, which is before all.</hi>
                  </hi> And this in deed is the true Antiquitie, that we muſt imbrace: this is the <hi>old way,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Prophet exhorteth vs to <hi>walke:</hi> this is the <hi>way,</hi> which Chriſt by his Prophets, his Apoſtles &amp; word hath taught vs, &amp; this indeed is the <hi>oldeſt way.</hi> In compariſon of which, the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Poperie is <hi>new</hi> and lately inuented, as will appeare, if we doe make a briefe diſcourſe through the principall points of religion now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</p>
               <p>And firſte to beginne with our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Iuſtification.</note> The ſcripture teacheth that we are conceiued in ſinne, borne in ſinne, brought vp and nouſied in ſinne, by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, death &amp; damnation, bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; ſlaues vnto Sathan. The <hi>olde way</hi> and onely <hi>true way</hi> to be deliuered from death, and to bee receiued into Gods
<pb facs="tcp:4545:14"/>
fauour againe, is by our Lord and ſauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Who alone is the ſeede of the Woman, that broake the Serpentes heade:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Who alone is the ſeede of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, and Iacob: In whome all the nations of the earth are bleſſed:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſaie. 53.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone was wounded for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſaie. 63.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and broken for our iniquities: Who hath troden the wine preſſe himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and of all the people, there was none with him:</hi> Who in the fulneſſe of time, came as it were out of the boſome of his father, toke vpon him our nature, was borne of the virgin <hi>Marie</hi> without ſinne, and in our nature, did not onely fulfill the Lawe of God moſt abſolutelie: (which we ſhould doe, and can not doe, by reaſon of the corruption of our fleſhe) but alſo in the ſame nature, did moſt obedientlie ſuffer moſt cruell death vppon the croſſe, to that end, that if we effectuallie beleeue in him, his puniſhment ſhould ſtande in ſteede of our puniſhment, his righteouſneſſe, in liew of our righteouſneſſe in the ſight of God. This is the <hi>old</hi> and only <hi>good way</hi> for ſinners, to obteine gods fauour againe. For the Scripture teacheth it:<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>So God loued the world, that he gaue his onely
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4545:14"/>
begotten ſonne: that whoſoeuer bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in him, ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math 11.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Come vnto mee all ye that trauell, and are heauie laden, and I will refreſh you.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.25</note> 
                  <hi>Wee are iuſtified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus, whom GOD hath ſet forth, to bee a reconciliation through faith in his blood.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ephe. 2.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>By grace are ye ſaued through faith, and that not of your ſelues: it is the gift of God, not of woorkes, leaſt anie man ſhoulde boaſte himſelfe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Io. 2.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>If anie man ſinne wee haue an aduocate with the father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, &amp; he is the propitiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our ſinnes.</hi> By which places and ſuch like, it appeareth plainly, that the efficient cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the fountaine and welſpring of our iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, is the loue &amp; mercie of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God: the matter and fourme, price and merit, is Chriſtes obedience, death &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: the finall ende is the glorie and praiſe of God, and our endleſſe ſaluation in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes kingdome: the inſtrument or hande, wherewith God dooth reach vnto vs ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from heauen in Chriſt Ieſus, is the Goſpell, and the preaching thereof: The inſtrument or hand, whereby we take hold
<pb facs="tcp:4545:15"/>
of Chriſte and his merites, is a true and liuely faith in Chriſt our Sauiour: The fruites of the ſpirite woorking in vs, and the true effectes of a iuſtifying faith, are vertuous and charitable deedes. Of which Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>Sequun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur iuſtificatum, non praecedunt iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candum. Good workes followe in him, that is iuſtified, but goe not before in him that is iuſtified.</hi> If this be the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>oldeſt way,</hi> whiche aſcribeth all our ſaluation wholy to Chriſte his merites: it followeth, that that is an <hi>erronious</hi> and <hi>lately founde out way</hi> of the Papiſtes, which attribute ſome parte of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to our owne worthines, to the merits of Saintes, to the woorkes of ſuperero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to the ſufferinges of Martyrs laide vppe in the Popes treaſure houſe. For though the ſufferinges of Martyrs, be the ſufferinges of Chriſte, and in them Chriſt doth ſuffer in his miſticall bodie: yet this ſuffering is not the price of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor anie parte of it, but his death and paſſion, and blood that he ſhed in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bodie vppon the croſſe once for all. <hi>Saint Auguſtine: tract in Iohann. 84. Etſi fratres pro fratribus moriamur, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4545:15"/>
in fraternorum peccatorum remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem nullius ſanguis Martyris fundi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Albeit, one brother die for an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet is the blood of no Martyr ſhed for remiſſion of ſinnes.</hi> And in the ſame place: <hi>Imitari quis potuit morientem, nemo autem redimentem. In dying, ſome man might followe Chriſt, but in redeeming, no man coulde follow him. Leo</hi> alſo a Biſhoppe of Rome, in three places affirmeth the ſame. <hi>Epiſtola. 97. <hi>ad Leonem Auguſtum.</hi> Epiſtola. 83.</hi> to the Biſhoppes of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> &amp; in the twelfth, Homilie of Chriſtes paſſion: <hi>That no Saint, by his death, did pay an other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s debt. For, that was onelie the office of Chriſt</hi> (as <hi>Baſill</hi> ſaith) <hi>who alone was voide of ſinne, and he alone the vnſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Lambe of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the worlde. As for the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes of Martirs,</hi> they <hi>are</hi> (ſaith <hi>Leo) Patterns of Patience to others, but merit no righteouſnes.</hi> And this he ſayeth, to the greate impoueriſhing of the treaſure-houſe of merites, and no ſmall diſcredite to Popiſhe pardons. Let vs therefore follow the counſel of the Prophet <hi>Ieremy, Stand vpon the wayes and conſider. &amp;c.</hi> It is
<pb facs="tcp:4545:16"/>
an <hi>old way</hi> ſhewed vnto vs by GOD him ſelfe, that all men ought to read and learne the Scriptures. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>This is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, to know thee the only true God, and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> And he commandeth <hi>To ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, for they are they, that beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of him.</hi> And <hi>Hierome</hi> ſayeth in the Preface to the Prophete <hi>Eſaias, That not to know the ſcriptures, is not to know Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> vppon the <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſ. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </hi> willeth <hi>Lay men</hi> to gette them the Bible into their houſes, as the wholeſome medicine of their ſoules: If not the whole Bible, yet the new teſtament at the leaſt. <hi>Audite obſecro ſeculares om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, comparate vobis Biblia, animae pharmaca. &amp;c.</hi> And he imputeth the cauſe of all euill, to the ignoraunce of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Therefore it is a <hi>new way</hi> lately founde out, that ignoraunce is the mother of deuotion. Let vs therefore folowe the Counſell of the Prophete, <hi>Stand vpon the wayes and conſider. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is an <hi>old way,</hi> wherein Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue walked, to beleeue that al things needefull to ſaluation, are conteined in the worde of God. This Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> teacheth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4545:16"/>
the <hi>cap. 20. <hi>Many other thinges did Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which are not written in this booke:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Sufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</note> 
                     <hi>but theſe are written, that you might beleeue, that Ieſus is the ſonne of God, and that in beleeuing, you might haue life by his name:</hi>
                  </hi> Which woordes <hi>Cyril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> expoundeth thus: <hi>Non omnia quae dominus fecit, conſcripta ſunt, ſed quae ſcribentes, tam ad mores quám ad dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata putarunt ſufficere. All is not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that Chriſte did, but ſo much as the writers thought ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as wel to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as to doctrine. Saint Aug. de doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina Chriſtiana. <hi>lib. 2. Cap. 9.</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith, <hi>In his quae aperte in ſcripturis poſita ſunt, inueniuntur ea omnia quae continent fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem moresque viuendi. All thinges conteining faith and manners, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly ſet downe in the ſcriptures. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius de fidei confeſſione</hi> ſaith. <hi>Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta eſt elapſio a fide, &amp; ſuperbiae crimen, aut reprobare quid ex hiis quae ſcripta ſunt, aut ſuperinducere quid ex non ſcriptis. It is a manifeſt ſliding from the faith, and a great pride, either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect any thing that is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the worde of God, or to bring in any thing vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>For Chriſtes ſheepe heare his voyce,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:17"/>
and wil not heare the voyce of an other.</hi> And in his Morals he ſaith, <hi>That if what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not of faith,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.4.</note> is ſinne, if faith come by hearing, hearing by the worde of God, whatſoeuer is brought in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the worde of God, is not of faith, and therefore ſinne.</hi> This <hi>olde way</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, to contente our ſelues with the truth of Gods worde.</p>
               <p>But it is a <hi>by way</hi> lately found out, to clog the Church with vnwritten verities, &amp; to make the traditions &amp; conſtitutions of the Romiſh Church, as neceſſarily to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and receiued, as the ſcriptures of God. Therefore it is good for vs, in this point al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to hearken to the counſell of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie, To ſtand vppon the waies, and conſider, to inquire of the olde waies, which is the beſt, &amp;c.</hi> It is an <hi>old way</hi> ſhewed vnto vs by God him ſelfe,<note place="margin">The marriage of Miniſters.</note> that the Miniſters of Gods word may pleaſe him in the holy ſtate of Matrimonie, inſtituted in Paradiſe by almightie God himſelfe, the firſt <hi>Prieſt</hi> that coupled man and wife togeather in holy Wedlocke, honoured by our Sauiour Chriſt in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 2.</note> not onely with his bleſſed preſence, but alſo with the firſt miracle that he did. <hi>S. Paule</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:4545:17"/>
ſaith, <hi>Marriage is honorable among all men, and the bed vndefiled,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 13.4. 1. Cor. 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>and they that haue not the gift to liue continently, are cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelled to marrie. Ignatius</hi> Scholar to Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt, in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Philadelphians,</hi> deſireth of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, <hi>to be receiued in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, and to ſit but euen at the feete of thoſe that were married men, and pleaſed God highly in that holy ſtate: As Abraham Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Eſaias, and other Prophets of God:</hi> As <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> and other Apoſtles. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> alſo vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That matrimonie is ſo precious a thing, that therewith a man may be exalted to the high ſeate of a Biſhop. Gregorius Nazianz, in monodia in Baſilii vitam,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That. S. Baſils father being a married Biſhop, was nothing hindred thereby from doing his office.</hi> The ſame <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> alſo in the funerals of his father, ſayth, <hi>That he beeing a married Biſhoppe, was much holpen in his office by the wiſdom &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his wife, Gregories mother. Sozomenus, <hi>lib. 1. cap. 11.</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith, <hi>That Spy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridion a godly biſhop had wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and yet nothing hindered by them
<pb facs="tcp:4545:18"/>
in his calling, but was ſo holy that he wrought miracles, Theophilactus</hi> vppon the. <hi>8. chap.</hi> of <hi>Matthewe: Peters wiues mother was ſicke. &amp;c.</hi> Learne heere, that Matrimony is no hinderance to vertue: for the chiefe of the Apoſtles had a mother in Lawe. But the Papiſtes ſay, that the Apoſtles left their wiues, when they folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Chriſt and preached the Goſpell. But Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth, <hi>1. Cor. 9. <hi>That Peter and the reſt of the Apoſtles, did carrie their wiues about with them.</hi>
                  </hi> So dooth <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> an olde writer, ſcoolemaiſter to <hi>Origines</hi> about <hi>1300.</hi> yeares agoe, vnderſtand the place in the <hi>3.</hi> booke. <hi>Clemens</hi> alſo Biſhop of Rome in the ſeuenth booke (if it be his booke, as the Papiſts ſay it is) ſayth, <hi>That Peter did carrie his wife about with him, when he went about preaching.</hi> For truely if the Apoſtles, after their calling, ſhoulde haue caſt of their wiues, they ſhould haue doone contrarie to the Canons, that are called <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nones Apoſtolorum</hi> (of which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes make great account.) The ſixth ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is this: <hi>Epiſcopus, aut preſbiter vxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem propriam nequáquam ſub obtentu religionis abiiciat. A Biſhop or prieſt may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4545:18"/>
not in anie caſe put away his wife, vnder colour of religion.</hi> And the Councell hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Gangra in Paphlagonia,</hi> about the yeare of our Lorde <hi>324.</hi> dooth accurſe them, that thinke a married Prieſt, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his marriage, may not offer, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to receiue, if he miniſter.</p>
               <p>The generall Councell alſo at <hi>Nicea</hi> in the yeare <hi>318.</hi> dooth allowe the opinion of <hi>Paphnutius: That it is Chaſtity for one to keepe companie with his owne wife.</hi> And the ſixth general Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel <hi>diſt. 31.</hi> decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>That Prieſtes and Deacons, ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at their orders taking, be compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to vowe a ſingle life, nor after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to be ſeperate from their wiues.</hi> And <hi>Simmachus</hi> Biſhop of Rome, he ſaith, as <hi>Gracian</hi> reciteth <hi>diſt. 81. <hi>Volumus vt ſacerdotes prohiberi debeant, ne cum mulieribus conuerſentur, excepta matre ſorore, vel vxore. We will that Prieſtes ſhall not be conuerſant with any woman, except ſhe be his mother, ſiſter, or wife.</hi>
                  </hi> And this to be the <hi>old way,</hi> the verie gloſſe it ſelfe confeſſeth: <hi>Loquitur ſecundum antiqua tempora. Hee ſpeaketh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to times long agoe paſt.</hi> In which <hi>olde waye</hi> notwithſtanding the
<pb facs="tcp:4545:19"/>
Prieſtes of the Eaſt Church haue <hi>walked</hi> and <hi>doe walke</hi> vntill this day. And ſurely if the Priſtes of the Latine Church had walked in the ſame, albeit their worldely pompe had not beene ſo great, yet the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of their life had beene nothing leſſe than it is. For true it is, that is ſaid in the Councel at <hi>Baſil,</hi> penned by <hi>Aeneas Syluius</hi> afterwarde Pope of Rome, and called <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Multi ſaluarentur in ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio coniugato, qui ſterili in preſbiteratu damnantur. Manie Prieſtes might bee ſaued in matrimonie, which beeing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, are condemned.</hi> The ſame Pope, (as <hi>Platina</hi> writeth) had often times this ſentence in his mouth: <hi>Magna ratione ſacerdotibus ablatae ſunt nuptiae, ſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iori reſtituendae videntur. There was great cauſe to take marriage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prieſtes, but greater, to reſtore it vnto them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Alfonſus</hi> alſo the Spaniſh Frier confeſſeth plainely, <hi>That marriage by the inſtitution of God, is no hinderance to Prieſthoode.</hi> Wherefore if this be the <hi>old way</hi> ſhewed vnto vs by the woorde of God,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.3.</note> that Matrimonie is lawful for al ſorts of men: We may conclude with Sainte <hi>Paule, That to forbidde marriage is the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4545:19"/>
doctrine of Diuels:</hi> that it is <hi>a newe way</hi> leading to perdition,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note> to forbid a thing that is honorable amongſt all men: and to wincke at fornication, which is deteſtable before God: <hi>Si non caſte tamen caute:</hi> To giue a diſpenſation, to keepe a Concubine, which can not be diſpenſed withall, and not to permit a lawfull wife, which needeth no diſpenſation. <hi>But let vs ſtand vppon the wayes and conſider, inquire of the olde waies, which is the beſt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is an <hi>old way</hi> ſhewed vnto vs by God himſelf, to direct al our praiers vnto God:<note place="margin">Prayer vnto God.</note> All the praiers in the olde Teſtament and in the newe, are wholy and onely made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. And ſo we are commaunded to do. <hi>Pſal. 50.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Call vppon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi> Chriſt taught his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to pray vnto God:<note place="margin">Math. 6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Our father &amp;c:</hi> He willeth them, <hi>To aſke in his name, and it ſhalbe graunted them</hi> S. <hi>Paule.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note> 
                  <hi>1. Tim. 2. That there is one mediatour betweene God and vs. <hi>1. Iohn. 2.</hi> If any man ſinne</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we haue an aduocate with the father Ieſus Chriſt the righteous,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and he is the propitiation for our ſinnes.</hi> As for praier to the Saintes departed, or to anie Angell,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:20"/>
we haue neither example, nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement in all the ſcripture. The Angell <hi>Apoc. 19.</hi> refuſed to bee woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of his felowe ſeruaunt.<note place="margin">Apo. 19.10.22.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine de vera religione, <hi>cap. 55.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Honoramus Angelos charitate, non ſeruitute. We ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Angelles in louing them, not in dooing ſeruice vnto them.</hi> And of the Saintes departed he ſaith. <hi>Honorandi ſunt Martyres propter imitationem, non adorandi propter religionem. We muſt honour the Martyrs, ſo that wee make them patterns, to imitate and follow, we may not woorſhip them in way of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Chriſoſtome</hi> commendeth very much the woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 15.22.</note> for that ſhe came not to the Apoſtles for her daughter, but directly to Chriſt. <hi>Vide prudentiam mulieris, non rogat Iacobum, non obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat Ioannem, non pergit ad Petrum. See the wiſedome of the woman, ſhee dooth not entreate Iames, ſhe dooth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech Iohn, ſhe goeth not to Peter, but directly to Chriſt.</hi> And in the ſame place, <hi>If thou haue a ſuite to a man, thou aſkeſt what he dooth, and whether he be at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or no? And thou heareſt that either he is a ſleepe, or not at leiſure, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4545:20"/>
the ſeruant will not vouchſafe to giue thee an anſweare: But if thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to God thou ſhalt need none of theſe thinges, neither miniſter, nor Porter, nor mediatour. Chriſt alone, both God and man is the onely Mediatour, both of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and interceſſion. Auguſtine <hi>lib. 2. cap. 8.</hi> contra <hi>Epiſt. Parmeniani,</hi> Pro quo nullus interpellat ſed ipſe pro om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, hic vnus veruſque mediator eſt. He that praieth for al, and none for him, he is the onely and true Mediatour. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius: contra Colliridianos. Ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das de ligno, etſi pulchrum eſt lignum, non tamen ad eſum: etſi pulcherrima eſt Maria, et virgo, et honorata, non tamen ad adorationem nobis data, ſed ipſa a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorans eum, qui ex ipſa carne genitus eſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou mayeſt not eate of the tree (ſaid God to Adam) though the tree bee faire and pleaſant to behold, yet is it not giuen to be eaten on: So, though the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie be moſt beautifull in al vertue, an holy virgin, and honorable, yet was ſhe not giuen to be woorſhipped, but ſhe her ſelfe did woorſhip him, which was borne of her as touching the fleſhe.</hi>
                  </hi> He ſayth further: <hi>Sit in honore Maria: pater,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:21"/>
filius, et ſpiritus ſanctus adoretur, Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am nemo adoret. Let the virgin Marie be had in honour: the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt muſt be woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: as for the virgin Marie, let no man woorſhip her.</hi> All the Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> all the praiers of the godly, throughout the whole ſcripture, are directed vnto. God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. And in deede this is the <hi>olde and ſafe way,</hi> warranted by the woorde of God. As for the inuocation of Saintes, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of this <hi>way,</hi> is a very <hi>newe waye</hi> though it be found in diuers auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But it is a <hi>way</hi> found out of verie late tyme, to turne all the Pſalmes of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> into praiers to the virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and to turne and chaunge <hi>Dominus</hi> into <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> the <hi>Lorde into our Ladye</hi> as <hi>Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentura,</hi> a ſchooleman of great eſtimation among the Papiſts, hath doone. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: Where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the fourth Pſalme. <hi>Heare me when I call, O God of my righteouſnes, &amp;c. Bonauentura</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauentura</hi> his Pſalter. Pſal. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Cum inuocarem exaudiuiſti me domina, et e ſublimi ſolio tuo mei dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata es recordari. When I cried, thou heardeſt me, O our Lady, and vouchedſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to remember mee from thy highe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4545:21"/>
throne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.1.</note> Where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the ſixtenth Pſalme, <hi>Preſerue me O Lord, for in thee haue I put my truſt. Bonauen.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me, O our Lady, for in thee haue I put my truſt.</hi> Where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith in the 54. Pſal. <hi>Saue me, O god, for thy names ſake, &amp; auenge me in thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 54.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Bonau.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Domina in nomine tuo ſaluum me fac, et ab iniuſtitiis meis libera me. Saue me O Lady for thy names ſake, &amp; deliuer me from mine vnrighteouſnes.</hi> Where <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, in the <hi>110.</hi> Pſalme: <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto my Lord, ſit thou on my right hand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.1.</note> 
                  <hi>vntill I make thine enemies thy footeſtoole Bonauentura</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord ſaid vnto our Lady, O my mother, ſit on my right hand, &amp;c.</hi> And not onely the Pſalmes of <hi>Dauid</hi> turneth he thus, but alſo the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the praier of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias, Te Deum, Benedictus, Benedicite, Quicunque vult,</hi> and the whole Letanie. And yet notwithſtanding theſe blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth of that name, did canonize this <hi>Franciſcane</hi> Frier for a Saint, in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1482.</hi> But this is a <hi>new way,</hi> and a great way about, to turne our praiers from God moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, moſt mightie, moſt able to helpe vs,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:22"/>
and moſt willing to heare our praiers, and to poure them out, not onely vnto the dead, (who whether they heare vs or no, we can not tell) but alſo to ſtockes and ſtones, which haue eyes and ſee not,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> eares, and heare not, mouthes and ſpeake not, handes, and handle not, feete, and walke not.</p>
               <p>But it is true that foloweth in the ſame Pſalme: <hi>They that make them, are like vnto them, and ſo are all they that put their truſt in them.</hi> Let vs therefore <hi>ſtand vpon the wayes and conſider.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Lordes Supper.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>old way</hi> to miniſter the Lordes ſupper, is that, which our ſauiour Chriſte did goe in himſelfe, and commaunded his Apoſtles to <hi>walke</hi> in alſo, ſet downe in the <hi>26. <hi>cap.</hi>
                  </hi> of <hi>Sainte Matth.</hi> the.<note place="margin">Math. 26.26. Mark. 14.22. Luke. 22.19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> 
                  <hi>14</hi> of <hi>Sainte Marke.</hi> the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>Saint Luke,</hi> and the <hi>11.</hi> of the <hi>1. Cor.</hi> That Chriſte, in the ſame night that he was betrayed, toke breade, and when he had geuen thankes, hee brake it, and gaue it, ſaying: <hi>Take, eate, this is my bodie, whiche is giuen for you, doe this in remembraunce of me.</hi> Likewiſe, after Supper, he tooke the cup, and when he had giuen thankes, he gaue it them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>This is my blood of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is ſhed for manie, for remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4545:22"/>
of ſinnes, doe this, as ofte as ye ſhall drinke it, in remembraunce of me: for as ofte as ye ſhall eate of this bread and drinke of this cuppe, ye ſhew the Lordes death, vntill he come.</hi> The Apoſtles li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked well of this forme of miniſtring the Lordes Supper, and did nothing ſwarue from it. They were not curious, nor cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious, but the faithfull being gathered together, after ſome exhortation, they reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the wordes of the inſtitution, and ſaide the Lordes prayer, and ſo diſtribution was made to all that was preſent. <hi>Platina</hi> in the life of <hi>Sixtus</hi> the firſt ſaith. <hi>Nuda primum haec erant, &amp; omnia ſimpliciter tractabantur, Petrus vbi conſecrauerat, oratione Paternoſter vſus eſt.</hi> Speaking of the Lordes ſupper: <hi>Theſe thinges</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were naked at the beginning, and all was handled ſimplie and plainely, Peter when he had recited the inſtitution, ſaide the Lordes prayer.</hi> Loe: this was the Malſe that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaied. That which <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> ſpeaketh of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſame doth <hi>Gregorie</hi> affirme was the vſuall maſſe of al the Apoſtles, <hi>lib. 7.</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhoppe of <hi>Syracuſa.</hi> But afterwarde this Simplicity by little &amp; little, began ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:4545:23"/>
offende the ſucceſſours of the Apoſtles, that in continuance of time al was turned vpſide downe, the ſubſtaunce taken away, and the name loſte. Firſt, a litle of the Name: then I wil ſpeake of the Subſtaunce it ſelfe. The Names vſed in the ſcriptures, are theſe: <hi>The Lordes ſupper, the body and bloode of Chriſte, the bread and the cuppe of the Lorde, the Lordes table, the participati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body and blood of Chriſt. Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Martyr</hi> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> call it <hi>Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia, thankesgeuing.</hi> It was named alſo <hi>Synaxis,</hi> by reaſon of the aſſembling togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the faithfull, to receiue it. And the whole action was called <hi>Liturgia, The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lordes ſupper.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout foure hundred yeares after Chriſte, in the <hi>Latine</hi> Church it beganne to bee called <hi>Miſſa:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The worde <hi>Miſsa.</hi>
                  </note> But for what cauſe, there are diuerſe opinions. Some ſay that it is an Hebrew word, and deriued of <hi>Maſas:</hi> for <hi>Mas</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Tributum, a tribute paide vnto the</hi> Prince. And this interpretation agreeth well vnto the Lordes Supper, wherein we offer vp vnto GOD the ſacrifice of prayſe and thankeſgeuing, for the redemption of mankinde, by the death and paſſion of our Sauiour Chriſte, as a tribute and bounden
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4545:23"/>
duetie, that we owe vnto God: But ſome had rather haue it deriued of <hi>Naſas,</hi> whiche is <hi>to lift vp:</hi> and <hi>Nes,</hi> in <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſignifieth a <hi>ſtandard</hi> or <hi>banner.</hi> For this they thinke doeth agree very well vnto their Maſſe, wherein they lifte vp Chriſte (as they ſay) in forme of breade, to be woorſhipped of the people, and offer him vp to God the Father, for the ſoules in purgatorie. And they would faine finde their Maſſe in the ſcripture, and therefore alledge the. <hi>16. Chap.</hi> of <hi>Deutro. Thou ſhalt kepe a ſolemne feaſt vnto the Lorde, with a voluntary lifting vp,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 18.10.</note> 
                  <hi>or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of thy hande.</hi> The <hi>Hebrew</hi> worde is <hi>Miſsah.</hi> Loe ſay they, the verie <hi>name</hi> of our Maſſe, is in the olde Teſtament. But I merueile, why they are ſo fond, to thinke, that this place maketh anie thing for their Maſſe, ſeyng that that <hi>Miſsah,</hi> which the <hi>Iewes</hi> offered vp in the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> was not Chriſts bodie, (which then was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne) but certaine loafes of breade made of their newe corne, whereof ſome were le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueined, and offered vp vnto the Prieſtes vſe? Or why abhorre they in their Maſſes. Leueined bread, vſed in the Iewes <hi>Miſsah,</hi> ſith they will needes borrowe their maſſe, from the <hi>Miſsah</hi> of the Iewes? The thing
<pb facs="tcp:4545:24"/>
of it ſelfe (I graunt,) is indifferent whether wee vſe Leauened or vnleauened bread, at the Lordes table. But ſurely the Popiſh Maſſe ſhoulde come ſomewhat nearer to the <hi>Miſsah</hi> of the Iewes, if they woulde not vtterly condemne leauened breade, nor deny the ſubſtance of bread to remaine after conſecration. But the beſt opinion is, that <hi>Miſſa</hi> is a Latine woord. And in this opinion is <hi>Polidorus Virgilius, Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Rhenanus, Michael Ritius, Iſydorus, Iſpalenſis</hi> and <hi>Rahbanus. Michaell Riti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>lib. 2.</hi>
                  </hi> Of his ſtorie of the French kings, ſayth, <hi>Antiquitus in vano deorum ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitione, peracta re diuina, conuerſus ad plebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſacerdos aiebat <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulis miſſio, quo verbo poteſtatem facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat abeundi volentibus. Idem mos a noſtris etiam ſeruatus eſt, vt libo iam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bato, pronuncietur per miniſtrum, Ite miſſa eſt, ilicet, ire licet. In the time of the olde ſuperſtition of the Gentiles, the ſacrifice being offered, the Prieſt turning himſelf vnto the people ſaid, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 1. Populis miſſio, the people may depart. The ſame cuſtome is obſerued amongeſt vs Chriſtians, that after the ſacrifice offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the miniſter ſhall ſay, Ite miſſa eſt.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4545:24"/>
That is to ſay: Goe, ye may departe.</hi> For <hi>Miſſa</hi> was vſed for <hi>miſſio:</hi> as in <hi>Tertulli. Cyp.</hi> and <hi>Optatus</hi> often wee reade, <hi>remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa peccatorum,</hi> for <hi>remiſsio.</hi> It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alſo, that the whole action of the Lords ſupper was deuided into two parts. To the firſt part were admitted, not onely the faithfull Chriſtians, but alſo Nouices and learners called <hi>Cathecumeni,</hi> as yet vnchriſtened: And not they onely, but Iewes, Gentiles, heretikes and notorions offenders. But when the ſermon was done, and the Epiſtle and Goſpell read, and certeine other praiers, and the Prieſt readie to goe to the Lordes ſupper, then the Deacon cried, <hi>Ite miſſa eſt.</hi> At which woordes all departed, ſauing the faithfull communicantes. Of this we reade in the fourth Councell holden at <hi>Carthag. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus nullum prohibeat ingredi in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, &amp; audire verbum Dei, ſiue Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilem, ſiue Iudaeum, ſiue haereticum, ante miſſam Cathecumenorum. Let the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe forbid no man to enter into the church, and to heare the word of God, whether he be Gentile, or Iewe, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, before the Nouices bee ſent away.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4545:25"/>
Then after the communion was done, the Deacon cried once againe, <hi>Ite miſſa eſt.</hi> By which woordes he gaue them leaue to depart, which had receiued the Lordes ſupper. Of this wee reade in Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Marcellina. When the Cathecumeni were ſent away, word came to me</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that the ſouldiars were in armure. Ego tamen in officio manſi, &amp; miſſam facere coepi, Yet for all that, I continued ſtill in the office of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and beganne to doe maſſe.</hi> In which place, this woorde <hi>Miſſa doeth</hi> ſignifie the latter parte of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or miniſtration of the Lordes Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, after the <hi>Cathecumeni</hi> were ſent away. This woorde <hi>Miſſa,</hi> ſo often ſoundinge in their eares, being the laſt woorde pronounced vnto them by the Deacon, and the woorde whereby they were diſmiſſed, and the woorde (whiche ſome, deſirous to bee gone, did long for to heare, of all other woordes,) was made ſo familiar vnto the people, that the whole action by them was called <hi>Miſſa.</hi> And after the learned alſo vſed the ſame woorde. And as the Deacon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4545:25"/>
did twiſe pronounce <hi>Ite miſſa eſt:</hi> Firſte when he ſent away the learners not chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened, then when they were diſmiſſed that had communicated: ſo did they deuide it into two maſſes. The firſt was called <hi>Miſſa Cathecumenorum, The maſſe of the learners or hearers:</hi> The other, <hi>Miſſa fidelium, The maſſe of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> This I take to bee the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation and occaſion of vſinge this woorde <hi>Miſſa.</hi> For the interpretation, that Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> maketh,<note place="margin">Innocentius 3.</note> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together fooliſhe. <hi>Ipſum ſacrificium, id eſt, hoſtia, dicitur miſſa, quaſi tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa, primum nobis a patre per ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctificationem, poſtea patri a nobis per oblationem. The ſacrifice or hoſt, is called Miſſa, becauſe it is ſente ouer firſt from the father vnto vs, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, then from vs to the father, by oblation, &amp;c.</hi> Loe, he maketh a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe ball of Chriſtes bleſſed bodie, in one day to bee toſſed from heauen to earth, from earth to heauen aboue tenne thouſand times. For in euerie maſſe, it is ſent vp and downe, and if at one inſtant ſome Prieſtes doe conſecrate, and ſome
<pb facs="tcp:4545:26"/>
do ſacrifice: at one inſtant it is ſent vp and downe, which is a miracle, not much mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the Papiſtes themſelues. But to ceaſe to ſpeake of <hi>Nocentius,</hi> mee thinke I heare a Papiſt ſay: Is the maſſe ſo old in deede? And did Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſay maſſe? Yea ſurely, S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaide maſſe, he confeſſeth it himſelfe, it can not bee denied, his owne bookes are extant. But I adde, that that maſſe which he ſaid, was not the Popiſhe maſſe worthelie ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of England, but the old maſſe, &amp; indeed a communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The Popiſh Maſſe.</note> As for the late Popiſh maſſe, it was more hundred yeares in the wombe of the Romiſhe Church, while it was conceiued formed, faſhioned and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, than is the Elephant yeares in the dammes bellie, or man monethes in his mothers wombe. It was not made alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, but patched vp by little and little: <hi>Celeſtinus</hi> made that part, that is called <hi>Introitus, the beginning of the maſſe,</hi> about the yeare of the Lord <hi>430. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> the firſte made manie prayers in the maſſe, and appointed <hi>Kyreeleſon</hi> to bee nine times repeated, about the yeare of our Lorde <hi>590. Gelaſius</hi> appointed <hi>Graduale</hi> to bee ſounge, about the yeare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4545:26"/>
of our Lorde <hi>500. Pelagius,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of the dead, <hi>Anno Domini 560. Eutichianus</hi> is ſaide to haue made the <hi>Offertorie,</hi> almoſt three hundred yeares after Chriſte. And one <hi>Adam de ſancto victore,</hi> a Monke of <hi>Paris</hi> the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenties,</hi> of late time. <hi>Leo</hi> the thirde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that in paine of depriuation, the Prieſtes ſhould not ſay maſſe, no not in the day time, without a candle: and that the altar ſhoulde be cenſed with franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, <hi>800.</hi> yeares after Chriſt. Moreouer the holy <hi>Canon</hi> (as they call it) of their maſſe, is not of that antiquitie, that ſome ſuppoſe it to be. <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſeemeth to ſay, that one <hi>Scolaſticus</hi> made it. But <hi>Faſcicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus temporum,</hi> and <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirde, ſay that <hi>Gelaſius</hi> was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall compilar of it. So that by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of two Popes, (whoſe witneſſes is good againſt themſelues) there was no ſuch <hi>Canon</hi> in the Church certeine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, as is vſed nowe in the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhe maſſe. <hi>Polidorus</hi> thinketh that no one Pope made it, but that a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Popes one ſucceeding an other, put to their helpinge handes, and made it ſuche a creature, as it nowe appeareth.
<pb facs="tcp:4545:27"/>
The ſame <hi>Innocentius</hi> the thirde is he, which in the yeare of our Lorde <hi>1215.</hi> concluded in a Councell at <hi>Laterane,</hi> that by the woordes of conſecration, the breade and wine were chaunged and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiat into the bodie and blood of our Sauiour Chriſt. Which ground being ſuerly laide, they would not ſtay there, but builded vp ſtill the tower of <hi>Babel.</hi> For his ſucceſſour <hi>Honorius</hi> the thirde, about the yeare of our Lorde GOD, <hi>1218.</hi> appointed the Sacrament to bee lift vp ouer the Prieſtes head, and the people to fall downe and worſhippe it, and to ſet vp their Idoll in the higheſt throne of maieſtie. <hi>Vrbanus</hi> the fourth in the yeare of our Lord GOD, <hi>1262.</hi> did inſtitute that great ſolemne and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall feaſt, called <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, wherein the Sacrament ſhoulde bee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about in proceſſions in a monſtrant made for that purpoſe, that the people might ſee it thoroughe the glaſſe. Hee graunted alſo, that all they that did fall downe and worſhippe it, ſhoulde haue pardons for manie dayes. And to make all thinges perfect. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> made a peculiar office or maſſe for <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4545:27"/>
Chriſti:</hi> as <hi>Platina,</hi> and <hi>Onuphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> doe teſtifie. Loe, theſe are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of the Popiſhe maſſe, and thus hath it bene patched vp by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. As for the maſſe, <hi>de quinque vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neribus,</hi> they will neither haue Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles, nor any mortall man, to bee the maker of it in earth: For the verie maſſe booke it ſelfe ſaith, that it came downe from heauen, and was ſent to Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> lying ſicke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his bedde, by the Archangell <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaell</hi> with this meſſage from GOD, that whoſoeuer, being ſicke of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſickneſſe, ſhould cauſe the ſaid maſſe to bee ſaide for him fyue times, he ſhould recouer his health: And if it ſhoulde bee ſaide likewiſe fiue times for anie ſoule in Purgatorie, by and by it ſhoulde bee deliuered from thence. This is ſett foorth in print in the maſſe booke it ſelfe, which was printed at <hi>Paris</hi> in the yeare of our Lorde, one thouſand fiue hundred and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene. If any man haue the booke, let him turne to <hi>Commune ſanctorum,</hi> and the two and twentith leafe, and there he ſhall finde it. But ſince that time (which was <hi>60.</hi> yeares agoe) the light of the Goſpell
<pb facs="tcp:4545:28"/>
hath ſo ſhined in the worlde: and ſo diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the darcke cloudes of Poperie, that in the later printes, for verie ſhame of the worlde, they haue left it out. Shall wee thinke that either Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, or Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or anie auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did euer ſay anie of theſe maſſes, which either were clouted vp by ſo manie Popes, ſo manie yeares after Chriſt, or ſodenlie at once inuented to mainteine and increaſe ſuperſtition and idolatrie? Is it not good counſell, that the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> giueth vs in this place, <hi>To ſtand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the wayes, and conſider, to aſke of the olde wayes, whiche is beſt, and to walke therein, that wee may finde reſt vnto our ſoules?</hi> That which Chriſt did, and commaunded his Apoſtles to doe, that are wee ſure is good. But the chiefeſt pointes of the Popiſh maſſe (as tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, the deniall of one part of the Sacrament to the lay people, ſacrifice propitiatorie for the quicke and the deade, and priuat maſſe) theſe thinges were not once dreamed vppon, in the primitiue church. Is it like that the Apoſtles at the laſt ſupper,<note place="margin">Math. 26.26.</note> when our ſauiour Chriſt ſitting with them, toke breade, and after giuing of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4545:28"/>
thankes gaue them, ſaying: <hi>Take, eate, this is my bodie, which is giuen for you,</hi> did once imagine of tranſubſtantiation?<note place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</note> They had bene brought vp in the Lawe of God from their infancie, which was open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reade in their ſynagogues euerie Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth day. They knew (no doubt) the vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all phraſe of the ſcripture, which giueth to the Sacrament the name of the thinge, whereof it is a Sacrament. Circumciſion was a Sacrament of the couenant, that God made with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and is called the Couenant.<note place="margin">Gen. 17.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Gen. 17.</hi> The Paſhall lambe, a Sacrament of the paſſing ouer of the Angell, and is called the <hi>Paſſouer. <hi>Exod. 12.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 12.11.</note> The Rocke which did yeeld abundaunce of water to the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell in the wilderneſſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 17.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Exo. 17.</hi> was a Sacrament of Chriſte the true Rocke, and is called Chriſte.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>1. Cor. 10.</hi> Baptiſme is the Sacrament of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde birth: and is called, <hi>The Lauer of regeneration: <hi>Titus. 3.</hi> Saint Cyprian de vnctione chriſmatis</hi> ſayth: <hi>Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantia &amp; ſignificata eiſdem vocabulis cenſentur. The thinges that ſignifie, and the thinges that are ſignified, ar called both by one name. Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,
<pb facs="tcp:4545:29"/>
                     <hi>Lib. 18.</hi> De ciuitate Dei,</hi> ſheweth a reaſon, <hi>Omnia ſignificantia videntur ſuſtinere perſonas earum rerum, quas ſignificant: Thinges that ſignifie, doe ſeeme as it were, to ſuſteine &amp; repreſent the perſon of thoſe thinges, whereof they are ſignes.</hi> And <hi>Epiſt. 23.</hi> to <hi>Bonifa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> he ſaith. <hi>Niſi ſacramenta ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem quandam haberent earum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quarum ſunt Sacramenta, omnino Sacramenta non eſſent. Ex hac autem ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudine, plerumque etiam ipſarum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum nomina accipiunt: ſicut ergo ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quendam modum Sacramentum corporis Chriſti, corpus Chriſti eſt, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum ſanguinis Chriſti, ſanguis Chriſti eſt: ita Sacramentum fidei fides eſt. If Sacramentes had not a likeneſſe vnto the thinges, whereof they are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, they were no Sacramentes at all. This likeneſſe is the cauſe that they haue the names of the thinges them ſelues: Therefore, as after a certein ſorte, the Sacrament of Chriſtes bodie is his bodie, the Sacrament of his bloode, is his bloode: ſo Baptiſme the Sacrament of faith, is faith. Bonifacius</hi> did aſke this queſtion of <hi>Auguſtine. When an infant
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4545:29"/>
cometh to baptiſme, they that bringe him, are demaunded, whether the child beleeueth or no? and the anſwere is made, that the childe beleeueth: How is this true, ſeing the child hath no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding? He anſwereth, that the childe doeth beleeue, becauſe it doeth receiue baptiſme the Sacrament of faith, whiche is called faith or beleefe: as the Sacrament of Chriſtes bodie, is called his bodie, &amp;c. Contra Adima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum <hi>Cap. 12.</hi>
                  </hi> he ſayth: <hi>Non dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit Dominus dicere: hoc eſt corpus meum, cum ſignum daret corporis ſui. Chriſte did not doubt to ſay: this is my bodie, when he gaue a ſigne of his bodie.</hi> And <hi>Tertullian, <hi>lib. 4.</hi> contra Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionem. Chriſtus acceptum panem, &amp; diſtributum diſcipulis ſuis, corpus ſuum illum fecit, hoc eſt corpus meum dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, id eſt, figura corporis mei. Chriſt toke bread and when he had diſtributed it vnto his diſciples, he made it his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſaying: this is my bodie, that is to ſay: this is a figure of my bodie. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doretus <hi>dialog. 1.</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith, <hi>That the Scripture vſeth to giue the name of the thinge to
<pb facs="tcp:4545:30"/>
the Sacrament, and the name of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament vnto the thinge. Chriſtes natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bodie is called breade, and his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall bloud is called wine: And contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, verie bread and verie wine, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his bodie and his bloude.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.51.</note> His bodie is called bread, when he ſaith: <hi>Panis quem ego dabo, caro mea eſt. The breade that I will giue, is my fleſhe.</hi> And <hi>Tertul.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Iewes, <hi>Lactantius</hi> alſo <hi>Lib. 4.</hi> and <hi>Hyerome</hi> vppon the <hi>11. Chap.</hi> of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi> to the ſame effect doe vnderſtande theſe woordes:<note place="margin">Iere. 11.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Mittamus lignum in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eius. Let vs put wood into his breade:</hi> which indeed are the wordes of the Iewes, that conſpire againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> and take counſell to mingle poinſonfull wood into his meate, to deſtroy him. But becauſe the conſpiracies againſt Gods Prophetes, were figures of that wicked conſpiracie of the Iewes againſt our Sauior Chriſt, theſe fathers whom I haue rehearſed, applie that ſentence vnto Chriſte: Againſt whom, when the Iewes did crie, <hi>Crucifige, crucifige, Crucifie him, crucifie him,</hi> in effect they ſaide: <hi>Mittamus lignum in panem eius. Let vs put wood into his bread,</hi> or
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4545:30"/>
faſten his bodie vnto the croſſe. <hi>Loe,</hi> ſay they, <hi>his naturall bodie in this place is called breade. Theodoretus</hi> likewiſe, to proue that his naturall bloude is called wine, doeth alledge the woords of Iacob, <hi>Gene. 49.</hi> Who ſpeaking of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.11.</note> that was to bee borne of the tribe of Iuda, ſaith, <hi>Lauabit in vino ſtolam ſuam, &amp; in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine vuae veſtimentum ſuum. He ſhall waſh his garment in wine, and his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell in the bloodde of the grape. This propheſie,</hi> ſayth <hi>Theodoretus was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, when our ſauiour Chriſt the true vine, did ſheade for vs his moſt precious bloude vppon the croſſe, which bloude iſſuing and deſcending aboundantly out of his precious woundes his handes and ſide, did waſhe his bodie, whiche was as it were the mantell and veſture of his godheade, Neither ought it</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſeeme ſtraunge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that his bloude ſhoulde bee called wine, becauſe Chriſte ſayth of himſelfe: Ego ſum vitis vera.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>I am the true vine.</hi> Nowe it is certeine, that the iuyce of the vine tree, and as it were the bloode of the grape, is wine.
<pb facs="tcp:4545:31"/>
And as the naturall bodie of Chriſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led breade, and the naturall bloode of Chriſte is called wine: ſo verie breade in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, is called his bodie, and verie wine indeed is called his bloode. For ſo <hi>Theodoretus</hi> concludeth in theſe woordes. <hi>Qui quod natura corpus eſt, triticum &amp; panem appellauit, &amp; vitem rurſus ſeipſum nominauit, is ſymbola &amp; ſigna quae videntur appellatione corporis &amp; ſanguinis honorauit, non naturam quidem mutans, ſed naturae gratiam adiiciens. He that called his naturall bodie wheate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 12.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn. 12. <hi>and breade,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 6.48.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn. 6. <hi>and himſelfe a vine,</hi> Iohn. 15. <hi>he gaue this honour to the ſignes,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 15.1.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſymbols which are ſeene, that he called them, by the name of his bodie, and bloode, not chaunging the nature, but adding grace vnto nature.</hi> But why did Chriſt chaunge the names of bread and wine, and called them his bodie and blood? He anſwereth, <hi>That he chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the names, for that he would haue them that are partakers of theſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly miſteries, not to conſider the thinges that are ſeene, but to haue their mindes fixed vppon the thinges,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:4545:31"/>
whoſe names they beare, and to beleue that chaunge, which is by grace.</hi> And <hi>Dialog. 2.</hi> he ſayth: <hi>Signa myſtica poſt ſanctificatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non recedunt ſua natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, manent enim in priori ſubſtantia, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura, &amp; forma, &amp;c. The myſticall ſignes doe not depart after conſecration out of their nature, for they continue in the ſame ſubſtance, figure, and forme, &amp;c. Gelaſius</hi> alſo a Biſhoppe of Rome wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt <hi>Eutyches,</hi> ſayth: <hi>Certa Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramenta quae ſumimus corporis &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis Chriſti, diuina res eſt, vnde &amp; per eadem diuinae efficimur conſortes naturae: &amp; tamen eſſe non deſinit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia panis &amp; vini. The Sacramentes whiche wee receiue of the bodie and bloode of Chriſt is an holy thing, and therefore by the ſame are we made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the diuine nature, and yet there ceaſeth not to be in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t bread &amp; wine.</hi> This no doubt, was catholike doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine in the dayes of theſe fathers, this was <hi>thold way,</hi> that our Sauiour taught them: But the Papiſtes haue found a <hi>new way,</hi> that the wordes of conſecration being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, the bread &amp; wine are tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat into the reall bodie and blood of Chriſt.
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4545:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yea into Chriſte himſelfe, yea into God him ſelfe, <hi>per concomitantiam.</hi> For ſo we reade in the Legend of Saintes, added vnto <hi>Lombardica hiſtoria.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Three kindes of power.</note> 
                  <hi>There are in God three kindes of power, magna, maior, maxima. As for example. The great power of God appeared, when he made one thing of an other, as man of the earth, and woman of the ribbe of man: But the greater power of God appeared, when he made heauen and earth of nothing. But this is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt power of all, that one creature, of an other creature, ſhould make the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour: And this power is giuen neither to Angell nor Archangell, but to the holy Prieſtes.</hi> What is blaſphemie, if this be not blaſphemie? Surely I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell. God that made all thinges, is not made himſelfe, neither can he make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for if he could be made, he were not God. And ſhall a ſinfull miſerable Popiſh Prieſt, in a corner take vppon him to make the maker of all? Let vs therefore giue eare vnto the Prophets counſell. Let vs <hi>ſtand vppon the wayes and conſider, inquire of the olde wayes, which is beſt, and walke therein, and we ſhall finde reſt</hi>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:4545:32"/>
them, that the people did receiue the Lords ſupper in both kindes? And ſo they doo in the Greeke Church vnto this day. <hi>Gabriel Biel,</hi> a ſchoole Doctor confeſſeth, that this inſtitution continued in the church a greate while, neither can he tell, when one kinde beganne to be vſed firſt, nor how it came in. And <hi>Alphonſus</hi> confeſſeth alſo, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had beſtowed greate paine to know, how and when the people began firſt to receiue in one kinde, yet coulde he not finde it out. And ſurelie, it was neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to be hereſie, to keepe Chriſtes holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, before the Councel at <hi>Conſtantia</hi> in the yeare of our Lord <hi>1417.</hi> Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſtand vpon the wayes, and conſider, aſke of the olde wayes. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdlie,<note place="margin">Sacrifice.</note> Chriſt in his laſt ſupper did not ſacrifice for the quicke and the dead, for the ſinnes of the whole world, for that did he once for all, vppon the altare of the Croſſe. Which oblation beeing moſt perfect, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can nor needeth to be repeated. For repetition is an argument of imperfection <hi>Heb. 10.</hi> Moreouer whereas there are foure thinges to be conſidered in Sacrifices (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>Quis? Quid? Cui?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.3.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4545:33"/>
                  <hi>pro Quibus? Who dooth offer? What dooth he offer? To whom? And for whom? Who dooth offer? A Prieſte: What dooth hee offer? A ſacrifice: To whom dooth he offer? vnto God, to whom onely ſacrifice is due: For whom dooth he offer? for men that are ſinners.</hi> In all others theſe foure thinges are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct one from an other: Firſt the Prieſt: Secondly the Sacrifice: Thirdly almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, to whom, and fourthly ſinful men, for whom ſacrifice was offered. But in Chriſt only theſe foure did concurre in one: Chriſt was the Prieſt, Chriſt was the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, Chriſt was all one as touching his diuine nature with the father, to whom he was offered, and as touching his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature (ſinne onely excepted) all one with vs, for whom he offered him ſelfe. And with this one oblation, hath he made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect for euer, thoſe that are ſanctified, as ſaith Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Heb. 10.</hi> For the continuall memorie of which ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.1. and 10.</note> he did inſtitute the holy ſacrament of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bodie, and bloode, to continue in the Church vntill his ſecond comming, for our full redemption: <hi>Doo this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4545:33"/>
of me: And as oft as ye ſhall eate of this breade, and drinke of this cuppe, ye ſhewe the Lordes death vntill his comming.</hi> It is true, that the olde fathers with one conſent call it a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice: But they expounde themſelues not to meane of a real offering, of a reall bodie, really preſent: But of a Sacrament of that real oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which he made once for all vppon the Croſſe. For as it is called the body and blood of Chriſt, both in the Scriptures, and in the auncient writers, becauſe it is a holy ſacrament of Chriſtes body and blood: ſo is it tearmed of the olde writers, a Sacrifice, and the ſelfe ſame ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, that Chriſt did once offer vppon the Croſſe, becauſe it is a Sacrament of that oblation, to put vs in a thankefull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce thereof. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> and Saint <hi>Ambroſe doo ſay, That wee offer vppe Chriſt daily: But we doo it in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his death, and worke a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of that ſacrifice.</hi> He was offered vppe once: But this ſacrifice is, as it were, a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie drawen out of the firſt originall, to put his death and paſſion alwaies in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo in the <hi>20.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4545:34"/>
booke againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> ſayeth, <hi>That the Iewes before Chriſtes comming, in of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering vp the ſacrifices appointed in the law, did promiſe and propheſie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes oblation vppon the croſſe.</hi> Chriſte when hee died, did perfourme it in deede: and we Chriſtians, now after his aſcention into heauen, doe celebrate the memorie thereof in the Lordes Supper. But the Papiſtes are not content with this: But they ſay, they haue him really preſent, and holde him vp, in their handes, in the ſame quantitie, that he was vppon the Croſſe, though not after the manner of quantitie, and reallie offer him vp to the father.<note place="margin">They that thus bragge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes captuitie, would hold him captiue.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brulifer</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quem totus mundus cape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non poteſt, noſter captiuus eſt: non er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, dimittamus priuſquam quod peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus obtineamus. Whom the whole worlde cannot conteine, is now our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue: therfore let vs not let him goe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he haue graunted our requeſt.</hi> This and ſuch like blaſphemies, wherin they giue to creatures the honour due to GOD, they call <hi>Spirituall daliance.</hi> But it is indeede more than daliance: for it is plaine <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fornication.</hi> Therefore let vs followe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4545:34"/>
the Prophets Counſel. <hi>Stand vppon the waies and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, aske of the old waies, which is beſt. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſt of all,<note place="margin">Communion.</note> Chriſte did not inſtitute a priuate Maſſe, but a Communion: he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all that was preſent to take and eate: he commaunded them all to drinke. In the Church of <hi>Corinthus</hi> and in all Churches many hundred yeares after Chriſte, it was the action of the whole Churche, wherein many eating of one breade, ſhoulde bee made one myſticall bodie. It appeareth by <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr,</hi> in his Apologie to the Emperour <hi>Antonius</hi> for the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Cyprian, Ambroſe,</hi> and the <hi>Liturgies</hi> that goe abroade in the name of <hi>Iames,</hi> of <hi>Baſil</hi> of <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> and the oldeſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that when the Lordes Supper was miniſtred, there was ſome parcell of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture read, a Sermon made vnto the people, a collection for the poore: and all that was preſent did communicate. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui myſteriorum particeps non eſt, improbus et impudens adſtat. Hee is an impudent looker on, that beeyng preſent, doeth not communicate.</hi> This was Catholike religion in thoſe dayes:
<pb facs="tcp:4545:35"/>
But now in Poperie, without preaching, without teaching, without ſenſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in a tongue that the Prieſte himſelfe vnderſtandeth not, in a corner without Communicantes, one eateth and drinketh all. Howe muche therefore are we bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to geue God moſt harty thankes, that hath mooued the Queenes Maieſtie, her Councel, the Cleargie, Nobilitie, and Commons of this Realme, that they, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing good eare vnto the Prophet <hi>Ieremies</hi> Counſell in this place, haue <hi>ſtoode vpon the Wayes, &amp; conſidered, haue aſked of the olde wayes, which is the beſt?</hi> and haue reſtored vnto vs, the olde, auncient, Catholike, and Apoſtolike religion, as well in other principal pointes of doctrine, as in the Lordes Supper, and haue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vnto vs, not an halfe or mangled Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but the whole Supper, not a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and idolatrous ceremonie, to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiate the holy ſignes into Chriſtes naturall bodie and blood, but an holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament inſtituted by Chriſte, wherein we feede on Chriſte, we eate his bodie, wee drinke his blood ſacramentally, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, effectually, and ſufficiently, to the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4545:35"/>
ſpirituall nouriſhing both of our bodies and ſoules to eternall life: Not a propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorie ſacrifice for the quicke and the dead, (that greate grounde of Popiſhe Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie) but a liuely memorie and repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſtes death, vntill his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming. God for his Chriſtes ſake make vs thankefull, continue his Truth and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie amongeſt vs, and graunt, that as ſhee cannot bee ſpoyled of this marke of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie,</hi> ſo it woulde pleaſe him euen for his Chriſtes ſake, that ſhee may finde ſuche fauour among men in earth, that ſhee may weare openly the other two badges, I meane <hi>Conſent</hi> and <hi>Vniuerſalitie.</hi> God bleſſe the Queenes maieſtie, Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, with many and proſperous yeares, conuerte or confounde all her enimies, and giue all vs grace, that bee here gathered togeather for this holy purpoſe, that wee, bearing a feruent loue, towardes almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie GOD, a dutifull obedience towardes her Maieſtie, and her Lawes, and vnfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned charitie one towardes an other, come not to this holy table, for faſhion ſake to pleaſe the worlde, but of verie good zeale to God and his worde: That we receiuing
<pb facs="tcp:4545:36"/>
theſe heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly myſteries to our endleſſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, may dwell in Chriſt, and Chriſt in vs, may be one with Chriſt, and Chriſt with vs, may be made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of his myſtical bodie in this life, &amp; in the life to come pertakers of his celeſtiall kingdome: Vnto the which he bring vs, that moſt dearely bought vs, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous: To whom with the Father and the holy Ghoſte, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; one true and euerliuing God, be all honour praiſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and power for euer and euer. Amen</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4545:36"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London at</hi> the three Cranes in the <hi>Vine-tree, by Thomas Dawſon, for</hi> Richard Sergier 1579.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
